rain man david
hey everybody welcome to the all in podcast  it was a slow news week so we decided we'd
give you a special episode we're gonna go around  the horn with our special picks we're each gonna
pick three picks everybody we're gonna pick our  favorite recipe our favorite new hobby and our
favorite streaming guilty pleasure because there  was no news uh with us today the dictator chamath
palihapatiya rainman david sachs with his new  track from young spielberg just ripping across the
charts uh young spielberg added again this time  with a a track focused on the rayman himself and
the queen of quinoa who everybody says  we should upgrade to the king of quinoa
that's so sexist why is that an upgrade the  queen of quinoa i don't know people just felt
i was being i don't know how people could say that  anointing him as queen would be derogatory i think
these people are not woke and they need to be  canceled jason here you go again making a lot
of assumptions about people's pronouns yeah they  they queen of quinoa they i take no offense i take
no offense your insults to me and uh today i'm  having the emotion of excitement and i am ready
uh for the conversation good we got the firmware  upgraded all right so uh i think we might as well
start with uh i don't know if you guys caught  this but there's a red subreddit called um wall
street bets and what they do on wall street bets  is they find angles and uh a thesis and then they
bet on a stock the stock they picked uh for  the past couple of months has been gamestop
and boy jason hold on a second um that's that's  that's not true so um do you uh i had actually a
guy on my team put together two really important  documents and i'm just going to read them
because it's full of so much interesting and  then we can talk about um where are these
from did you say from the wall street bats no no  no i had a guy go in uh one of my team members
one of my colleagues and go and summarize  the entire saga from the beginning and then
we can talk about the the corporatist scumbags  that robin hood and other [ __ ] people over
so let's let's do that in that way okay um this  is the way they call him the dictator let's uh
you're an idiot because you you just want to  defend people because you blindly stumbled into
a [ __ ] trade that actually made a little money  lo and behold you actually invested in a company
that literally they got on television yesterday  and they [ __ ] lied to americans right to their
face this is a company that was insolvent because  now let's just put a pin in the following data
point which i believe to be true i know more about  this than you do because i live in these markets
okay so i understand what it means to be putting  on trades to being short to being gamma-squeezed
to have longs to do all of this risk management  you're an early-stage investor so i know the
intricacies of this stuff and what's happening  in here this company was insolvent they did
not have the capital requirements to post the  margin that was being asked of them by their
partners and so this was a platform level decision  to ban and block people from trading securities
it cost individuals hundreds of millions  probably billions maybe even tens of billions
and these [ __ ] should go to jail now let me  give you the timeline before we get into that
june 2019 in june of 2019 a wall street  bets user named deep [ __ ] value
began buying long dated january 21 calls what that  means is in june of 19 this person was betting
that the stock would go up by january of 2021. he  spent 50 000 um which by the way today is worth
about 25 million dollars by the way we should just  highlight that there are forums where individuals
that are trading stocks talk to each other and  share tips and promote things to one another
that's where this was taking place yeah and by  the way those forums exist uh in the professional
organized world too amongst hedge funds you know  i've been invited to idea dinners where we all get
together and we talk about the ideas that we have  and we're all expected to do fundamental analysis
but some of those ideas are actually momentum  driven ideas and a lot of the biggest dislocations
in the market just as a setup here have been  because of momentum driven trading by organized
capital okay so we've we've been stuck with this  for a while so so this guy deep [ __ ] value
posts this and every month since he's posted a  screenshot of his position and he's titled it
gme yolo update august 22nd of 2019 michael bury  who is this guy famous from uh the big short
who's the guy that caught the mortgage thing he  discloses a three percent position in the company
and he highlights that ninety percent nine zero  percent of gamestop's 5700 stores are free cash
flow positive that's like pretty good he urges a  buyback and he notes that the company was trading
at or near net cash levels so he's making a deep  value oriented fundamental thesis as well i think
also it's worth saying what gamestop is because  even my wife asked me what the hell is gamestop
last night gamestop is a retail store where  people buy video games i used to go to the
mall all the time and consoles and headphones and  other stuff and they'll buy back your old games
and so the stock got beat up over the last  couple of years as people stopped going to malls
and stopped buying stuff in stores and everyone  thought the company was going to die and so these
guys observe that maybe there's real value in this  company and it's making money digital downloads
no one buys dvd roms anymore  or anything like that so
and and the chewy founder who is  very successful at e-commerce came in
june 19 was the original post august 22nd of  19 michael bury comes in and says i'm long
then a year later august 31st of 2020 ryan cohen  who's the founder of chewie takes an almost 10
position in gamestop about two or three  weeks later on september 19th of last year
a member of wall street bets writes a post on  gamestop and he notes that gamestop has a hundred
and twenty percent short interest which i'll get  to in a second so hold on what what does that mean
120 short interest and he defends the company as a  result of a few things he says number one there's
a new console cycle coming just as jason mentioned  number two consoles are are not going all digital
immediately gamestop loyalty programs have 55  million users they have a strong balance sheet
ryan cohen just bought a stake and the shorts  were underwater and would be forced to cover
if the stock ran up he predicted the convergence  of all these factors would lead to a big squeeze
now november 16th of 2020 ryan cohen writes a  letter to the gamestop board and he urges the
company to conduct a strategic review and share  a credible plan to capture market share in the
gaming industry he said that they need to evolve  into a technology company that delights gamers
and delivers exceptional digital experiences i'm  just quoting here not remain a video game retailer
that over prioritizes its brick and mortar  footprint and stumbles around the online ecosystem
november of 2020 someone in wall street bets  highlights that a hedge fund called melvin capital
was going long gamestop puts what does that mean  that they are synthetically shorting the stock
by buying the right to sell it at a different  price in the future okay um and that they had
been longed that position for more than four  years so all the way going back to 2016.
fast forward to now 2021 of  this year january of 2021
game stop strikes an agreement with ryan  cohen and adds him to the board of directors
and gives two of his affiliates his former  ceo and and cfo of chewie also two board
seats they collectively you know bring their  experience in e-commerce online marketing
finance and strap planning the stock goes up 13  on that day and closes at about 20 bucks a share
one day later and then over the next day after  that so for january 12th and 13th of 2021
there's a ton of activity around  gamestop in wall street bets
and now in discord and in stock twits claiming  that brian cohen is going to be the savior
and then by january 14th so three days later  the stock closes at 40 bucks so now it's up
125 so now comes the setup the pros versus  the joes from january 12th to today there has
basically been a battle by institutional  investors on one side shorting gamestop
and retail investors on the other buying the  stock and also buying the right to buy the
stock or what's called call options and this is  what has created this crazy nonsense we've seen
so on the institutional side after you know retail  drives the stock up the institutional guys are
like hey wait a minute you know ryan cohen's an  idiot you know this company is [ __ ] [ __ ] these
guys they have too many you know cyclical and  secular tailwinds and they become so massively
short that the infrastructure that's supposed to  even count all the shares can't keep up and now
they are short more than the actual number of  shares that actually exist so now they're 140
short the joes retail they start to aggressively  purchase all these cobble options and on january
13th and 14th um this price keeps ticking  up then a bunch of quant funds and momentum
hedge funds notice all this activity and  they also participate on the long side
and then over the past seven trading days we  have traded over 100 billion dollars of stock in
gamestock which is well in excess of what retail  can support so here's what's crazy to realize
a bunch of value-oriented non-computerized  non-quantitative hedge funds short retail notices
of dislocation initially fundamentally but then  momentum-oriented buys other hedge funds realize
also buy and this is what's created this massive  short squeeze on january 19th citroen research
a research firm that basically tries to you know  find shorts in the market announces that they
were short game stop and they gave five reasons  why it should go to 20 bucks the stock was at 35
50 on january 19th then over the next two days  gamestop calls hit an all-time high and it runs
a two-day rally of almost 70 percent and this is  what really starts what's called a gamma squeeze
okay which is what we saw in the first part of  this week so january 25th ken griffin stevie
cohen they inject almost three billion dollars  into melvin capital the firm that was short
two billion from citadel and 750 from from stevie  cohen stevie cohen had a billion in it from before
and then now all of a sudden the squeeze keeps  happening the squeeze keeps happening and then it
starts to spill over to the rest of the market now  all these hedge funds these original hedge funds
they are getting called by the bank saying hey  wait a minute you've run over your collateral
limits you need to post more collateral  we need more money in your bank accounts
so now not only do they have to cover gamestop  they have to cover all their other shorts so
those go crazy and they have to sell their longs  so now they're selling you know facebook netflix
alibaba so those things are going down that  accordion is what's been happening in the market
in the last couple of days and then the coup de  gras is what happened on january 28th of 2021.
brokerage firms and this is where jason we should  talk about this like robin hood and interactive
brokers because in fairness it wasn't just robin  hood prevented their users from buying gamestop
and a handful of other stocks they were only able  to sell which resulted in such a one-way pressure
it caused a 44 sell-off yesterday  now that's been reversed today
and so what it speaks to is a bunch of questions  there are questions as to whether or not this was
mandated by the platforms or the regulators given  the fact that it didn't impact all the brokerage
accounts it was a platform level decision so  some organizations like robinhood banned it
some organizations did not and it could be  that some of these platforms that banned it
is likely because and this is where  we get to the insolvency question
didn't have enough margin and so they knew that if  they opened the doors there would be a run on the
bank and there would be a run on robin hood and  that's why they basically i believe had to stop
um allowing people to trade and it  just shows how um how fragile um
the whole system is the last thing i'll say  and then we can talk about this is uh how
does robinhood make money which i think is also  important to understand this robinhood makes money
through a mechanism that's called payment  for order float so they don't make money from
consumers right what they do is they watch and  monitor your orders they create a data file about
that and they give it to these prime brokerage  prime brokerage institutions like citadel
milliseconds before you do the trade what  that allows citadel to do is if they see a
lot of people buying milliseconds before you  buy they can buy and that allows them to make
money so to be clear citadel is responsible for 47  percent of all the payment for order flow volume
they paid robinhood almost 60 million dollars in  the third quarter okay um plus another i think
you know seven and a half million for s p 500  stocks and 31 million for non s p 500 stocks
they paid them almost 100 million in the  quarter or a 400 million dollar run rate so
if we had to summarize all of this in a nutshell  that's what we know we know that it started out as
people debating the true fundamental value of  gamestop and it morphed into a momentum trade
where a bunch of folks got dogmatic about a short  a bunch of folks got dogmatic about being long
and belongs one and in the middle  what happened was a bunch of firms
basically decided at some point to gate the  ability for people to transact in all of this
which i think caused a lot of economic  disruption and that was because they didn't
have the margin requirements and i think  it's because they were insolvent i.e robin
jason over to you okay um i think we probably  agree on a lot of things here uh thank you for
the concise over we agree that wall street  vets and retail investors are incredibly
powerful now and we agree that that's a good thing  we also probably agree that there are shenanigans
going on with shorting of stocks i.e 120 or 130  percent short and we agree i think that some of
these uh hedge funds do manipulate the markets  with these we also agree that it's unfortunate
that uh in order to stay solvent robin hood  apparently if this is the information we don't
have complete information right now so the thing  i do think that you're being tremendously unfair
about and i'll try not to make it personal to mop  is that you've been uncouth and you're attacking
people without with partial information i'll let  you respond to that in a minute and i think we
agree that robin hood is responsible robin hood is  responsible for this revolution in retail trading
they created the platform and they created the  innovation that got millennials to on mass embrace
trading stocks how did they do it they figured  out a clever innovation of how to make it free
and friction free they did that because they  did this selling of the data in the order flow
okay we can debate whether that is fair or  not but facebook did the same thing they
created a data business they provided amazing  products and services that you yourself built
for five years and made a billion dollars off  of in order to make it free for consumers now
there are unintended consequences of any  company at scale whether it's uber robin hood
tesla etc and they will all have to weather  these storms and i think that there are pieces of
information that you do not have chamoth and for  you to say that they're criminal and for you to
say their scumbags and to act this way is i think  unprofessional does you a disservice and does your
argument a disservice and you did this as  well with uber another one of my investments
and that company weathered the storm and  they've done great things in the world
and they and i'm very proud of that no no no no no  no no and i will be very proud of what i believe
that and they brought in dara who cleaned  it up oh agreed agreed but they got there
and so well what happens so why do you know that  i don't know well i i haven't talked to vlad i
saw what he cares about vlad he lied on he lied on  television i don't believe he lied i liked it he
lied on fox where did he know his life yesterday  what is the lie well jason he was confronted about
whether there was a liquidity crisis and he  said to their face no that is not true i think
this is being misinterpreted and  there'll be a clarification that occur
i think because they were able to draw down  600 million and because they were able to
take down a billion dollar investment from the  top investors in the world that they s resolved
their liquidity problem nobody in history  has ever created this many retail investors
than robin hood they are responsible for the  movement when they pitched me the company
they wanted to create this revolution it is  paradoxical that they are now the enemies of
the revolution because they actually created and  enabled this and i pre and they have been number
one in the app store since this whole fiasco  nothing you're saying convinces me this is the
they are the lehman brothers or bear stearns of  2008 to me they will not be they will get through
this and there has this is an unprecedented  black swan event i think we would all agree
nobody had exactly what lehman and bear said that  is exactly what they said and this and they will i
believe robin hood will write it out because they  throttle the number of people coming to platform
las vegas is not designed for everybody in  america to come to las vegas in the same weekend
what's happened will you admit that that the tens  of millions of people that had their hard-earned
money inside of robin hood was prevented from  participating in trades that could have been
executed other places because of an arbitrary  decision by robin hood that they had it was an
arbitrary thing to stay insolvent how is that  how is that jason an arbitrary decision do you
think they wanted to make that decision jason  that's me telling you that they were insolvent
that's not them saying it this is what i'm saying  right now communication was not perfect i'll agree
the communication was not perfect they should have  just said we had no choice but to stop this or
we would have been insolvent we cannot take this  many trades is that but is that what we call lies
when people's money gets [ __ ] over just it's  inconvenient let me just say one thing i'm going
to interject your your your vigorous debate um the  the important thing i think to note is robinhood
makes money effectively as chamath pointed out  um through arbitrage of pricing in the markets
and by providing leverage to their clients so the  clients can trade beyond their means i used to
be an investor in a forex trading company  was the largest forex trading platform in
the world for retail investors and 60 of those  accounts went bankrupt uh over time so there was
a lifetime value on an account because the  uh the customer would come in they'd trade
foreign exchange rates up and down they would  ultimately just get burnt up and that was it
robin hood makes money when the market is  non-volatile when there isn't a lot of swings
suddenly when there is a swing and that's how  they're able to provide their free pricing to
people they're making a spread but suddenly when  there is a swing and the spreads start to widen
they are actually exposed to losing money so  jason it's true what chamath is saying like they
did face a liquidity crisis to some extent that's  why they had brought out they all agree but it was
a function of their business model right their  business model provides great benefit and value
in some extent during good times but when times  get bad it's like oh [ __ ] things are at risk
and that's very similar to kind of the lehman and  and you know i don't disagree i don't disagree
i i think this is an unprecedented situation with  the number of participants it reminds me of surge
pricing with uber during snowstorms and that also  was an unintended thing that you know who knew
that it would go up to 400 to take a ride and  that's something that companies will be faced
with and they will have to then adjust and then  make it work and i think you know in the case of
robin hood they should have just came up on  wednesday and said we can't take any more orders
we can't take any more new customers we're pausing  signups you'll be on a waitlist because we will
be insolvent if you guys make any more trades  and that would have i don't know if you believe
that would have i agree with that so jason let me  just communication it's beyond poor communication
people were blocked out of their accounts like  there was hundreds of mill incalculable amounts
of economic loss that i don't know if that's gonna  wind up being true because all these trades are
occurring now and the stock is rock is a rocket  ship who's to say that oh no i mean look i mean
jason aren't the shorts all covered by now that's  what they've been saying on cnbc no there are
still people how do you know how many people are  short right now and how many shares because it's
the primes put the data together and they send  it to us do you have it handy because i've been
looking for it online and they said ten times the  number of shares short have traded hands in the
last ten days or five years i mean jason i don't  know i don't have it literally in front of me but
i could get it in the next yeah just text one  of your people you've got all these researchers
there um go ahead zach okay look i'm going to  try and thread the needle here um i think j-cal
is right that um we shouldn't impugn people's  motives without having all the information and
furthermore you know building these uh rapidly  scaling startups is really tough and it could
have just been you know a function of you know  not knowing how to deal with unprecedented
growing pains so i don't think i don't want to  be too judgmental can i just stop people hold on
yeah nobody that's not right no but david  that's not can but you guys are not being
accurate they have known for decade for years  sorry dears how this business work when somebody
buys a call option they are legally  obligated when they send that order through
they have to post margin on behalf of that person  so they saw this building this happened in march
of 2020 they went through this liquidity crisis  they've had to draw credit lines before they saw
it building in the system so this was nothing  except negligence yeah so so i was about to
that i hadn't gotten to the part where i was  about to agree with you chamath i mean look
all i'm saying is even if it was negligence i'm  not sure i would impugn all the motives to them
that that's all i'm saying i'm trying to find some  common ground with j column that point but where
i totally agree with yuchimoth is with respect to  the effects of their decision i mean the effects
of that decision they made to stop trading and  specifically they didn't stop people from selling
they only stopped people from buying so they shut  down one side of the trade and the effect of that
was we had these hedge funds from wall street they  were on the ropes right i mean let's discuss who
these guys are these are the apex predators of  wall street they are in the business of shorting
companies to destroy them i mean that is their  business model and they are not academic traders
okay who are just speculating on outcome they  engineer the outcome right look at their tactics
just watch the show billions right they hire pr  people they hire private investigators they're
participating on these message boards uh spreading  disinformation look at the the year of hell that
elon went went through right they tried to destroy  like five years yeah yeah exactly they try to
destroy uh companies to engineer that outcome  they create nothing they're in the business of
of of destruction now the beautiful thing is you  had these reddit kids these pirates who published
this manifesto right on reddit basically being the  heirs to occupy wall street they recognize look
occupying like a like a physical space does  nothing to these guys we are going to hurt them
where accounts in their pocketbook we are going to  get together and we're going to basically create
a trade mob that's even bigger than their cartel  and they did they got 2.7 million people taking
the other side of this trade and then when the  hedge funds doubled down they said [ __ ] you
we're gonna double we're gonna triple down and  the guy on reddit said listen he uh paraphrasing
john maynard kane said we can be [ __ ] longer  than you can be solvent and they were winning
that was what they said right and they were  winning the trade okay and melvin was dead
busted and citron was on his way to being dead  busted and they had to go to big papa stevie cohn
okay and ken griffin to get to get their rebuys to  buy their revised to get back into the game okay
and then they had these guys on the ropes they  had them felted okay and then what happens
just at the moment where they're gonna like  basically bust them out of the game for good
robin hood shuts down the buy side of the trade  and so what does that do it gives these hedge
funds time to regroup to unspool the tray to  reposition and save themselves and to get out
of the trade if they want to get out of the trade  you can never take that 24 hour time period back
no matter what robin hood does now and so i agree  with jamaat this was like don't you this was
tremendous david on that point i think it's i am  in agreement that the hedge funds deserve to get
their assets kicked 100 i also as i said we don't  have complete information of why um you know robin
hood had to pause trading and the other platforms  and it was like five platforms by the way that
had to stop or else they would be insolvent  because nothing like this has ever happened before
this is a run that nobody's ever seen and now  we're back in the game and don't you think all
this attention then drives more people to buy  gamestop which is what's happening today and
that they're still going to get crushed because  they're still going to have to cover i mean
look i i i don't like like i said look where i  agree with you is i think the consequences of
this decision by robin hood were i mean they  were really bad right i mean we finally had
these shorts on the ropes where they deserve  to be finally they're getting a taste of their
own medicine yes and it was really bad to pull  the plug on on the though i wish they were they
wish they didn't have to i'm sure okay exactly  and i don't know what went into that decision
but here's the thing that i think kind of stinks  about it is the point that your mother is making
about who is doing the the trade execution  for robin hood those trades are flowing to
citadel well that's part who is that's part of it  but 40 47 but who is now on the short side of the
trade citadel went in and bailed out melvin and  citron and so they're on both sides of this trade
now how does that make sense well citadel yeah but  i mean what i would like to know specifically okay
is did anybody from citadel reach out and touch  robin hood did anybody at citadel put in the
fix and saying to robin hood of course that's a  good question we're gonna we're gonna cut you off
you know unless you freeze out the buy side now  look 99 chance that didn't happen i don't know but
that is a legitimate question we need to actually  can i just tell you the the question is important
but the way that you phrase it is you call them  and you basically say listen uh you need to post
500 million dollars of margin why oh well these  trades uh you know what we're going to arbitrarily
change the margin requirements okay oh eight  you need to raise uh you need to post so then
what they did was they pulled all the credit  lines okay they post margin trades are still
happening like crazy right all these people are  buying gamestop calls they have to go because look
when you buy a call when you as a user with david  friedberg quinoa buys a call robinhood becomes
synthetically shorted right robinhood doesn't have  the share to sell you but it's giving it to you
so they're technically short they got gotta go buy  it okay so this is what creates this dynamic where
robinhood knew they knew every second of every  moment what was happening and more importantly
what could happen at a minimum it's negligence  and at a maximum it's the fix well it was and it
was it was fine to do it before the market started  to swing volatile right and and so when the market
wasn't high volume and when it wasn't volatile  it didn't matter because they had appropriate
levels of surplus capital or statutory capital  or whatever the definition is in this market
uh to be able to cover the quote-unquote var or  the value at risk of their portfolio of their
customers worst-case outcome but as soon as that  spiked as soon as the var spiked they had to go
get more capital and so what do you do if you're  the manager of robinhood in that situation where
your clients who've been making you a bunch of  money by trading stocks over the last couple of
years suddenly they all get themselves in a bind  where the var on the portfolio is more than the
cash robin hood has to clear assuming all these  people go bankrupt that's where robin hood had
to scramble and so in that circumstance they drew  down debt and they had to go get a billion dollars
of equity but if you guys were running that  business and i'm not speaking for robin hood's uh
i'm not making the case for robin hood but what  would you guys have done in that circumstance
you know suddenly all your and by the way i'm  saying they created the problem for themselves
because they allowed people to trade on margin  with low bank with low account balances and
volatile stocks prior to this it got away from  them and because you can't you cannot run a
business like that and be selective and arbitrary  you can't say some stocks on certain days some
stocks on other days some options over here some  puts over there that means you're a [ __ ] [ __ ]
what do you do on tuesday or wednesday when all of  a sudden you're not tuesday wednesday this if you
were a reasonable manager of a business like this  this conversation would have been happening at a
board meeting quarters ago hold on a second let me  finish please okay it needs to happen quarters ago
and in quarters ago what they would have said  is hey guys we've run some scenario analyses
we've done some sensitivity analyses here's what  happens if all of these things can go against us
that's a typical stress test that a bank has to  do right when you're a structurally important
bank you have legislation that forces you to be  under these conditions where you have to make sure
that that you can understand some of these  scenarios and then you have any any trading
entity or insurance company they all have to have  that analysis of what's the worst case scenario
and how do you plan for it and you have to you  and by the way coming out of 2008 we actually
legislated that we needed to have these two and  three sigma you know event scenario planning and
you needed to have proper credit so here's what  happened really number one it was under equitized
right at a minimum the business was massively  relative to what they were letting their customers
do exactly and that's really important because the  point is they let people trade with high margin
and they let people trade in volatile  stocks and it was working until
not just stocks but options which is what which  is what creates the real spin up the feedback
loop that blows this whole thing up and and then  number two is they don't know what they're doing
i think one thing that's really  important i just want to say this
we should stop pretending that trading in  stocks is investing in businesses and uh this
is something we've said for a long time on wall  street but stocks shorting margin and derivatives
those um those four things no longer look like  what the capital markets were originally set up
for which was to help capitalize businesses and  allow people to exit their investment in helping
to capitalize that business to another investor  that wants to come along it has effectively become
a synthetic casino or a synthetic gambling model  that lets people trade things up and down and
this has been the mainstay of wall street for the  last couple of decades and as you pointed out saks
uh it really is a leech on the system because the  amount of money that trading firms and traders and
hedge funds make doing this ultimately is taking  away from capital that could be invested in actual
businesses that could drive job growth drive  economic prosperity drive innovation and um the
volatility that i think we've seen is the ultimate  feedback loop that emerges from when you allow
a casino to operate that sits under the guise of  being business capital and investing in businesses
it's not i'll give you guys a statistic i  downloaded the data from cboe that analyzes
how much volume was traded across all the  equity markets last year in the us stocks traded
a total volume last year are you guys ready  for this 121 trillion dollars of notional
um across 2.7 trillion trades do you think  that 121 trillion dollars of notional equity
value trading provided capital to businesses  anywhere close to one percent of that total
amount of trading volume it really is a synthetic  instrument that allows people to participate in
i bet that something is going to go up and  i bet that something is going to go down
with other people of an of a similar ilk and  one person makes money and one person loses
money and at the end of the day the underlying  business entity doesn't benefit whatsoever
and you see it when shorts go against  businesses like happened with elon and tesla
and you see it when derivatives like cdos blow up  the [ __ ] housing market where people basically
trade these derivatives that sit on top of  housing and that capital did not find its way
into homes to help people buy homes it ultimately  led to the uh collapse of the only the only reason
that lehman and bear stearns was shut down was  in 2007 and eight when they were in a liquidity
crunch in the same thing and they basically  had all these trades blowing up against them
and they couldn't collateralize them was that  the people on the other side were hedge funds
and that's why you know they were put into the fed  and that's why we were able to basically like you
know come out relatively unscathed and but i mean  by relatively unscathed is like a global calamity
um the the tragedy of this is that this is  the tragedy of the commons it's like you
know there is no organization of people that  can say hey listen i'm really rich and wealthy
and what happened here was wrong even though it's  probably on the same scale and so everybody that
was a participant in it is in in my opinion  i think is guilty of all of this they were
they were complicit in the robbing of america  do you think calls and puts um and shorting
should be allowed should those markets exist i  i do have a sense of common sense solutions and
let me uh let me kind of give you them and then  you can tell me what you think so the first
is we need to use modern technology let's  just start with that right to ensure that
you know one share of stock right isn't loaned out  multiple times so that you can't have a scenario
where you have more than a hundred percent no  brainer right that's a no-brainer so you still
support shorting some up yeah let me let me  just go through the list and then you can tell
me what you think if if high-frequency firms  can trade tens of millions of shares per day
there's no reason why we can't reconcile who  the beneficial owner of every share is so
maybe that's a you know now maybe we found the  first obvious use case for a blockchain right um
like you can't borrow a share unless you can prove  beneficial ownership in a in a you know nanosecond
which can only be done on a you know decentralized  ledger but the point is number one is we need to
rebuild this infrastructure you can't have 136  percent of a company be short that makes no sense
the second what we've learned is that again  the it's like are we going to basically have
these blow ups every 10 years before we actually  address the elephant in the room which is leverage
like you need to have leverage limits so for  example banks coming out of 08 have super strict
oversight and leverage limits and because they're  dubbed systematically important we don't do that
for hedge funds and i think we need to and i think  that we need to have the ability to realize that
these these guys can cause systemic risk right so  um just on this example i don't know if you guys
have ever heard about long-term capital management  yeah this guy john merryweather the asian
currency crisis the whole thing collapsed so good  there's a good book on it well so it's it's funny
but if you guys think this is the second financial  calamity it's not the first it's the third because
the first one happened in 1998 so in 1998 it was a  firm call it was the whole uh economic system was
going to collapse if the bailouts didn't happen  so listen to what these guys did long-term capital
management borrowed they had 4.8 billion dollars  of capital that limited partners and investors
gave them okay these [ __ ] crooks were able to  then borrow 125 billion dollars 125 billion on the
4.8 billion of notional so they were able to lever  themselves up 26 times by the way synthetic margin
right no actual capital was allocated to these uh  to this transaction uh set it was all synthetic
like no no money moved accounts when no money  moved accounts so it was literally just writing
stuff against debt that couldn't have existed yeah  so they so they built 60 000 trading positions
and those individual positions represented  again 1.4 trillion right us dollars
so you took these guys in a room took 4.8 billion  got knucklehead over here to give them 125 and
then got these knuckleheads to sell them positions  and all of a sudden 4.8 billion equaled 1.4
trillion and so then u.s u.s regulators  had to step in they had to orchestrate
a bailout from a consortium of banks because  they were concerned that if ltcm collapsed the
whole system would collapse because they didn't  understand so right so we have to we have to put
leverage limits on top of hedge funds the third  is we need to improve disclosure the the rules
at the sec right now is to discourage  disclosure that doesn't make any sense
we should force everybody to publish what they own  on a weekly or monthly basis you have the ability
to do it the technology is simple so you need to  imp improve disclosure because then watchdogs and
other people can basically be looking at it all  day and identifying these risks faster not slower
the third is we need to do  something around open trading
like why is it that you're you know people are  allowed to go to casinos why can you uh you know
buy lottery tickets um but all of a sudden like  we're gonna decide who's financially literate
a platform like robin hood can decide what's  bought and what's sold i don't think that's fair
um and then the last thing is i think that  we should have a short-term trading tax
um we tried to pass one in 2018 10 basis points  if you had passed this 10 basis point tax in 2018
on short-term trading it would have created a  trillion dollars almost i did the math on this
because i actually the reason i ran all the  equity numbers was to figure this number out
so in the u.s we generated 160 billion dollars in  capital gains tax last year and if you look at the
volume i described earlier in terms of notional  traded of equities and number of shares traded
if you charged 0.1 every time someone sold a share  on the value of the share they sold it would equal
the capital gains tax so what you could do is you  could charge 0.1 on every trade it would reduce
all of this high frequency nonsense where people  trade in and out of stocks it would force people
to trade for the longer term or basically invest  in companies and you could get rid of the capital
gains tax think about that if we didn't have to  pay capital gains tax and we were only taxed when
we traded out of a stock 0.1 percent you could  see an incredible amount of capital making its
way into businesses and this would fuel economic  growth and jobs and prosperity um and so i think
if you could pull that off put the two together a  0.1 percent sales tax on every share sold and get
rid of capital gains tax the lobby is incredibly  powerful the lobbyists got to that bill but that
10 basis point tax on high frequency trading it  just means like look if you're going to trade a
whole bunch of [ __ ] every eight seconds you just  have to pay 10 basis points in and out 777 billion
dollars of incremental revenue to the federal  government and it was lobbied out and i agree
with you and by the way the more more money goes  in more money makes its way into companies right
and that's the best you stop all the nonsense  where people are basically trading to bet that
something will go up in the short term and you  get people to make investments in the business as
opposed to the momentum lowering the capital gains  rate is genius because i think that if you if you
are a retail investor and you can for every year  you hold if you can decrease your cap gains rate
by 20 by the fifth year now all of a sudden retail  folks aren't necessarily gambling they're owning
and their cap gains rate would be zero  after five years that would be amazing
i i have a a basic question i'm interested in  your position saks and maybe even around the horn
what happens to the if the short positions get  covered which they're going to be at some point
in game stop i would think or some large amount  of when the short squeeze is off what happens to
the people who are buying in you know to the meme  stock as a retail investor let's say over the next
10 days are they going to be left holding the bags  is there any way this company could be worth 20
billion or 25 billion because as freeberg points  out there people are not buying gamestop they're
they're trying to destroy a hedge fund  uh who made a stupid manipulative bet
great we all love the the robin hood story of that  not robin hood tm but the generic term robin hood
um what happens to those people are they  gonna be the last people holding the bag
probably this is not going to end well there's no  question about that i totally agree with you that
people engaging in this kind of speculation and  buying at these prices it's not going to end well
now i do think that the redditors actually had a  brilliant strategy right when they noticed that
these hedge funds were over short overexposed and  they seized on that vulnerability they did to the
hedge funds what the hedge funds usually do to  everybody else which is find the achilles heel
right and pile in so i think the strategy started  brilliant now anyone who's piling into it i'd be
real careful because i think the hedge funds have  regrouped you know and um you know the idea that
you're gonna be beat them at their own game you  know when look i mean citadel is executing your
trades i mean right that the trades are the  order flow is going from robin hood to citadel
they're not going to be caught flat-footed they're  on the other side of this trade and so you know i
just think the house always wins i'd be real  careful about getting into it at this point
robin hood just tweeted that now the list of uh  restricted names is now up to almost 35 or 40.
i think it's worth um randomly picking companies  guys rlx what is rlx uh i think that's uh
ralph lauren nope you're  not allowed to trade that um
sndl i don't know what that is but you  can only buy 10 shares would a better
solution chamoth be for them if they can't  handle this and they have the risk of ruin
to just say we're not adding any more accounts  until we can digest all this and raise enough
capital to float all this and do you think there's  a chance the sec is telling them you got to pump
the brakes on this because we can't have a market  crash two questions jamal um i i think that the
the the issue isn't um robin hood uh ability to  grow it's that they don't have their ability to
run their business and so their incompetence is  gonna cause them to i think have to deal with
if they had well if they had 20 billion dollars  in cash right now this would not be an issue right
i think you're right okay so assuming they can  line that up because that's probably what's
going on right now is a 10 billion dollar uh  investment is going to go into this company
pre-ipo so that they can actually take advantage  of this situation and grow so despite the fact
that you have an axa ground with them because you  have sofia competitor that's very far behind them
that had its own colossal problems let's put  that aside for a second you're talking your
own book without even mentioning it do you think  that if they had that 10 billion they would just
open up all the doors or do you think maybe they  should say hey we're not going to add anybody else
i think that what's going to happen is  they're going to get sued into oblivion
i think that the class action lawsuits here when  people talk about the uh implied losses that that
they that they had over the last 24 hours david  sachs is right you can't undo it the thing is like
what in all of these other situations like in the  uber fiasco you know you can't claim much damage
right because you can't measure it you could have  taken a bus you could have taken a taxi you know
you could have taken a lift maybe you could have  walked who knows what it is but the point is that
the the economic impacts um i think were much less  than maybe the psychological impact right like you
were angry here it's the exact opposite which is  that you prevented people from transacting in an
open market and when people signed up to use  the service that's what they thought they were
signing up for and they thought that the risk on  the back end would be managed you have to remember
it's not that the individuals did  anything wrong by buying or selling
it's that robinhood did something wrong by not  being able to manage their business accurately
and then that then impacted the users to  the tune of tens of billions of dollars
that has to get adjudicated and so yeah  i think the right thing to do is to stop
the business hit the pause button allow people  to elegantly transfer their money out do we have
to remember on the back end of this whenever  that you have one of these market failures
the clearing houses are allowed to instantaneously  close your account and transfer to another broker
instantaneously you have that right and so the  market does understand the systemic risk at some
level they just didn't push it all the way through  to the end of retail and so we're going to have
to unwind this and unscramble this egg because  it's a really it's a really big problem yeah
you imagine growing growing willy-nilly because  everybody's infatuated with valuations and blah
blah and you move into a regulated market where  you needed to understand capital constraints you
needed to understand modeling you needed  to understand three and four sigma events
it just means you're under prepared which means  at a minimum you can't be doing business until
you get that [ __ ] under control yeah i i  actually think we're almost in sync on this um
you have a little bit of an axe to grind because  of your other portfolio company i think that you
still won't recognize that you have a way let's  talk about worse in the race wait because so far
i just did they did they finish resolving all of  their harassment lawsuits is that all resolved now
or is that still open yeah we've and then you  took them public so did did you work all that
out before you took them public yeah jason we  we transitioned the ceo we've completely hired
a new team um i mean it's incredible right  so you so your company that you took public
can resolve issues and you can give them time and  then you can in fact become their mentor and you
can become their savior to get them public and  save that company jason you should robin hood
can't jump robin who can't can't talk about  his company that's going public right now so
just as his lawyer i'm gonna step in and okay  no no make sure you don't go to him into saying
something companies all of our companies and i  don't mean to create a lot of collateral damage
here but sacks had a company that had challenges  chamata companies are challenged we've all had
companies have challenges and i think focusing on  what is the role of an investor when your company
faces challenges i think the role of the investor  should be and i take umbrage to you chama trying
to dunk on me because i'm supporting an investment  i think it's a low blow and i take it personally
i'll be totally honest i am trying to work with  the company to help them resolve the issues and
i need to be loyal to my founders and i need to  say hey how do we resolve this how do we get here
and work with them and you say that i'm right or  die but that's how i approach this is i should
be trying to be helpful as a shareholder could you  i think you try to be too but could you make the
argument that someone dunking on your company is  the equivalent of a hedge fund shorting a company
i'm talking about my personal relationship with  chamoth which you know it's different than you
know the the public markets right i know but what  i'm saying is like i think in the private markets
we hear a lot about venture investors um you know  often speaking good about their own companies
where people really get irritated is  when venture investors speak bad about
other companies it's the equivalent of  the hedge fund short and uh you know
jacob i mean chamoth may be dunking on robin hood  i don't hear him dunking on you i mean i just said
i stumbled into the investment at the opening well  you stumbled into vlad in a bar i mean you told me
jason you told the story jason you told the story  recognized me in a bar and came up in pictures
but you told the story flippantly on television  that you ran into man antonio's nut house what do
you want us to think you didn't tell us hey listen  i had i had systematic scouts reach out based on
traffic growth i sat down my that's not how i get  deal flow fine by doing a podcast decal if you
want me to apologize for your flower it's through  this jason but jason if you want me to apologize
for saying that you stumbled into it based on your  public description on television then i'm sorry
yeah but it doesn't but it doesn't take  away from what we have i i think the
investors responsibility this is what i think  is fundamentally wrong with silicon valley
we are people that basically do this like hero  worship around founders and it's stupid i think
we have a job as fiduciaries to the users and to  the employees and to everybody else that doesn't
have a voice and most investors are incapable  of actually pushing people to do the right thing
okay i'm pushing to do the right thing and i  always i've learned the hard way and in this
example what i'm saying is this problem should  have been solved three and four quarters ago
and that's a government yeah i mean look yeah  you said your mother you're right about that but
i mean just to give jkl a little support here  i mean the reality is you know we've all been
on the inside of these hyper growth companies and  you know like mistakes happen all the time because
you're moving so fast and yes it should have  it should have been fixed you know but but you
know stuff happens now the question is when bad  stuff happens is it an integrity issue or is it
negligence or is it just people running too  fast and i don't think we know that this was an
integrity problem i mean it could have just been  people running too fast but david that's what i
mean you knew what the rules were meaning i don't  think i think it is an integrity issue the rules
were not like all of a sudden in a crystal ball  and all there's a magic 8-ball that spits out a
rule when you do a deal with dtcc when you did  a deal with your holding company for clearing
you sign contracts those contracts should have  been modelable this is an excel problem this
is not i i i i hear what you're saying and i'm  saying i don't completely know i want to get to
the bottom of the relationship between citadel and  robin hood and i want to understand if there was
any undue influence there okay or whether this was  just a case of hyper growth catching a company by
surprise i'm not defending them i'm just saying i  don't know and therefore i think it's a little bit
premature to be talking about giving this company  and i also don't think is there even a possibility
that this has ever happened in the history of the  stock market or the modern stock market that's 10
million new and well done i even say what it is  10 million new retail investors came into a stock
you know where millions of them a day and that  the stock traded i don't think that we've ever
had social media collide with finance like this  and it's very reminiscent of our discussions with
democracy and journalism censorship and politics  we we're having weird behaviors because of
virality and i think that seems to me this is  the most important learning from this experience
forget about the fiduciary and the governance  responsibility of these companies whether they
were good or bad will be resolved over the  next couple of weeks and months i'm sure
as more information comes to light but what's  super interesting about what happened this week
and i think is the most impactful societally  over time um is that we're seeing this phenomena
where um individuals in aggregate can believe  something to be true and make it true and um
we saw this with tesla and i i don't think tesla  got this level of notoriety because it was such a
a longer play out cycle but elon you know was not  hitting numbers that people thought he was gonna
hit margins production volume etc people were  shorting the stock but enough people believed in
the story that elon told about what he wanted the  future to look like that they bought the stock and
that gave him the ability to do shelf offerings  raise additional capital and ultimately build the
business and make it manifest in reality that he  said would happen and the same is true of bitcoin
and the same is true of trump and the same is  true of storming the capital in all of these cases
there was a belief in something and there was an  aggregation of individuals using social media as
a mechanism for sharing and talking and engaging  and creating a collective outcome that wouldn't
have happened through a centralized system or a  centralized process and wouldn't have happened in
the traditional way where history defines the  future and i think that is what's so powerful
about what's happening right now and we're seeing  it in financial markets but we're also seeing it
play out in politics and we're seeing it play  out in the real world um in a remarkable way
and it goes back to this notion that like a stock  is worth the underlying value of the company and
that that's not true people can dream a stock to  be anything as they did with tesla at the time
that people were buying tesla stock the historical  performance of that business was not what hedge
funds considered to be a you know a profitable  good business it shouldn't be worth anything
but the belief in what it could be is what drove  the value of that stock and ultimately that value
enabled that business to become true um and it's  just it's it's amazing to see it happening and i
think the the counter which is really what makes  this so striking is the centralized institutions
that are trying to block this from happening and  um the shutting down of parlor and the shutting
down of robin hood trading are are equivalent  from my point of view um or at least equivalent
i think will be perceived to be equivalent broadly  which is if a group of people get together and try
and use an online service to make a change in the  world by sharing and talking with one another and
communicating a belief a collective belief and  that gets yanked away from them the institution
that has the ability to yank it away from them  is evil and it will force people to decentralize
and it will enable new ways of trading new  ways of communicating um new ways of building
um and and that's the profound change that i  think this decade is going to realize and we're
just seeing it start now i agree that parlor  or wall street bets is parlor 2.0 right and
and what happened as soon as wall street  bets started which is the the reddit kids
they started threatening and they wounded these  powerful insiders these rich you know hedge fund
magnates what happened they started getting  banned off of discord they got discord as
a tech company to kick them off how did that  happen they've been talking on there for months
and all of a sudden just magically right at  the critical moment where they're also not
allowed to trade their free speech gets cut off  that's a that that was deliberate now i'll tell
you how it happens is i guarantee you what  these hedge funds did is they went through
the discord room and they screenshotted you know  any post that they could plausibly characterize
as you know hate speech or what have you and you  know and and by the way i mean those there's a lot
of raunchiness in these rooms but it's not  hate speech and it's not organized for the
purpose of hate it's organized for the purpose  of trades but what they do is they weaponize
these censorship rules and they go in and they  screenshot and then they give it to discord and
they get these guys kicked off and this is exactly  what i've been talking about with censorship it
starts with something you like and then becomes  something you don't how many of the people
who support these you know reddit kids were in  favor of de-platforming trump and parlor and now
they can see where it goes this is slippery  slope and we've only had to wait three weeks
to see where it goes it goes to the same place  which is when the people in power get threatened
they use these rules they weaponize these rules  to shut down the outsiders and the upstarts
that is the problem with censorship that is why  you cannot let the beast get started i completely
agree and i think this is exactly why how i  think where we came out was you know the deep
platforming of trump made no sense i think the the  economic censorship of robin hood makes no sense
yeah and you can argue it's the right thing to  do with a narrow context but when you take the
broader point of view of the implications that's  where this becomes really shaky and really scary
and i think really enables a decentralized  movement that is going to be a lot broader
um than than folks are really realizing at this  point you know folks don't want to be trading um
on a system that tells them how to trade and folks  don't want to be communicating on a system that
tells them how to communicate if i gave if i was  running robin hood and i said uh we're going to
have two options there's going to be a robin hood  diamond membership and you pay by the trade and
you know you get these special features and then  the robin hood free you know you you get uh your
data is sold or however it works would that  be a possible solution i think to the optics
issue here where consumers could basically pick  just like if facebook or instagram woke up one
day and said for 9.95 a month you can have none  of your data no advertising ad free like hulu
hula premium i would so here's the thing j cal um  i i hope your robin hood investment is successful
i just think that there are now three moments in  robin hood's life there is pre this week and it
is what it is it's an 11 billion unicorn  god bless them then there was this week
where we have to frankly hold people accountable  for the economic damage that they created this
week because it is measurable okay it's not  that it's not like missing it you know um
uh it's it's not like you know surge pricing  in uber it's not you know uh facebook growing
too fast and allowing you know pictures of breasts  getting posted and i'll have to catch up it's not
that okay it's not a bunch of like disinformation  that we can't really judge this is very discreetly
judgeable and so in this week robin hood existed  as a different company and i think that there's an
implication for that then to your point honestly  i agree with you it's what happens from here and
i and they should survive but they have to learn  and i think what they have to learn is you have
to stop the account growth you have to massively  shore up the balance sheet take the dilution get
the capital you need because let's be honest i'm  sorry but nobody's gonna show up with five or ten
billion dollars at 11 billion pre they'll show up  at five or ten billion dollars at three billion
pre and they should take the money and then they  should allow the platform to work as intended or
at least as perceived to be intended to their  users and then they should reopen to everybody
what would you do david if you were in charge and  then let's move on to our next topic well i i mean
i i i i feel like we probably talked about robin  hood enough and i kind of want to go back to the
point that that freeberg was making just kind of  up leveling this a minute which is i i definitely
think this is part of this ongoing populism versus  the elite war and social media is now the tool
that the people use to organize themselves against  these powerful elites it's why we cannot allow
censorship because it always comes down uh it to  benefit the powerful the elites against the people
trying to organize against them that was for to  me one of the biggest takeaways from this week
and and look the reason why people are organizing  is they're asking the question what is the
societal benefit of these big hedge funds in  relation to the enormous sums of money they make
every year you go to like the forbes rich list or  whatever and every year these guys are taking down
the most money they're not creating companies you  know and chamath is right we can't have founder
worship because they make mistakes too but at  least founders are creating things right they're
taking big risks that they're not providing risk  capital like what we do okay we're investors but
we're funding people's you know we're we're taking  the risk of writing checks to to start the guy
who's got nothing right or gal yep you know they  them it's all all good all of them all of them
so so but try to keep you from getting canceled  here but but but but what it what exactly is the
societal value of these hedge funds now i know  that they provide some price discovery and they
provide greater liquidity to markets but is that  really worth them really being the richest players
in the game it doesn't make any sense and then  when they lose like in 2008 they get bailed out
it makes sense it makes no sense something  is wrong here now is this a right-wing view
a left-wing view it feels to me like there's a  political realignment happening here where the
left and the right we're all getting on board with  this idea and it's got to get fixed yeah this this
might be the legacy of trumpet way sacks that he  created so much disruption over those four years
that now we're actually finding out where the  actual breaking points are in society and this
is one of them and the healthcare system is one  of them and freedom of speech is one of them and
we need to address each of these and they're  complex but there is common ground i mean when
aoc and ted cruz are both agreeing uh on the  same issue with something's going on here like
i think we have to fight the real enemy chamath  and i should not be fighting over this because
i can tell you if chamoth did the series a and  this he would be backing up robin hood like this
to the end of the end of earth and that's  totally fine and i agree with jason i just
i just want you to know number one i love you  with all my heart and i and i hope you make it
i hope you i hope you make dinner hundreds  and hundreds of millions of dollars but
there's a it's just like you know you were you  just got upset with me because you thought i was
kind of saying that you stumbled into it i didn't  mean it that way i was just repeating the way that
i heard the story but something that touches  me equally ferociously is this idea of like the
little guy getting run over by some like you know  objective thing over here that makes a decision
that's arbitrary i'm 100 agreement with you and so  like the idea that like you know somebody who's on
an app all of a sudden gets censored somebody that  you know makes a post gets cancelled somebody that
all tries to make a trade can't it feels unfair  it feels that each individual is suffering some
pretty deep inequity yes and i can't i just can't  stand that it really just touches me in a way
that tilts me and i get very and you know what  it's interesting i think the reason i made the
robin hood investment is because my belief in the  underdog in my belief in people's ability to come
up from being poor middle class to middle class  or affluent freedberg you haven't chimed in yet
as we wrap here and then move on to our  second topic i think we're at an hour
so it's um so i just want to say um you know we  talked about decentralization and you know we
all feel the emotional response to the little guy  getting screwed by the big guy that controls the
system and we want to fight the system that's  the basis of every great movie um it's worth
highlighting though that decentralization and what  i would kind of characterize as swarming behavior
uncontrolled swarming behavior can actually have  negative consequences and there's a reason systems
exist you know um when you put a bunch of people  in a room let's say you put 100 people in a room
and every time and someone says the word door and  every time you hear the word door you're supposed
to repeat it within 30 seconds the entire  room will be like deafening with everyone's
screaming door door and suddenly everyone will be  screaming it that's a feedback loop that occurs
in an uncontrolled social system and that's what's  occurred with gamestop and it's what occurred with
with bitcoin so there are as we've seen remarkable  outcomes when you allow systems to operate without
centralized control and without centralized brake  pads that that kind of slow them down or put in
place some rules and some obligations to how that  system operates the problem with decentralization
and this swarming approach uh to to resolution  where lots of people basically work together
individually is you end up with things like  cancel culture where um before a judge and jury
determines whether or not someone did something  wrong the community decides that person should be
punished and shuts them down in the real world and  their career and their life is ended and ruined
and we saw the same and we saw the same with  the capital riots you know people basically died
because of the swarm that occurred where this  idea that the there was fraud in the election
became an echoing deafening noise for these people  and they swarmed and killed people and the system
by which you can actually have vigorous debate and  the system by which you can actually have controls
and processes and judges and juries and trials  is what needs to be improved for this to work
otherwise people will go to decentralization and  you will have a lord of the flies moment that
engulfs civil society because the tools are there  today and so centralized systems can work but they
have to adapt and adapt quickly to be fair and to  enable and to not um discriminate otherwise we're
gonna see lord of the flies and we're gonna see  decentralization being the solution to getting
out of the system that's inhibiting us and we're  gonna end up having really [ __ ] ugly outcomes
there's a psychological term for what you're  describing it's the diffusion of responsibility
when and also known as mob behavior when a  group of people collectively do something
their individual morality can evaporate and the  larger the group and the uh more intense the
behavior the less responsibility each person takes  for it so five people on the steps of the capital
you know one person breaks a window maybe somebody  breaks it but once you have 500 or 5 000 and one
person breaks a window now you got a much higher  percentage of people start breaking windows and
that's when tragedies happen of course world war  ii was the diffusion of responsibility with the
team yeah you're totally right yeah you're totally  here just just one quick point then we can just
move on yeah so i think these like viral tools  these social networks they enable two things they
enable mobs but they also enable movements i think  the mobs are bad and the movements are good or
they can be good depending on what their manifesto  and what their mission is and so i think we want
to enable the movements but we want to be really  careful about the mobs and you know one of the
things that's kind of disturbing about twitter is  i generally find that like the tweets that seem
to go the most viral are the ones that are full  of rage and anger and the ones that are trying
to make more nuance points just kind of get lost  and so there is something a little bit disturbing
about the mob behavior but but the movement the  enabling of these new movements i think is really
powerful and that's what wall street bets was  at least in the early stage and they did not
deserve to get shut down like that social social  networks are a collective amygdala they are not a
collective cerebral cortex and i think if someone  can solve that problem and get people to think
about the rational objective outcomes in a social  way in its engaging a fashion as it is to kind of
be excited by the negative shift that excites the  amygdala um you know it could be really powerful
but that's probably we're gonna need politicians  who we're gonna need some level of politician who
has some integrity and some expertise if  only well don't you think don't you think
don't you guys think that what this means  is that uh entrepreneurs now can really
think about decentralization as the key feature  like in many of these markets or these systems
where we have the centralized authority we  have to move to a much more decentralized
democratized way of doing things whether it's  stock trading or whether it's healthcare records
or whether it's you know education  systems and degrees and accreditation
there has to be a way where you can't morally  yeah but with morally and ethically inclined and
or legally inclined systems that ensure that the  behavior of that system doesn't run amok and you
know that's really where things can um can go can  go awry uh as we've seen lately um but it's a hard
problem to solve it i i don't think we're gonna  solve it here today just uh a final update fif
i don't know if this is exactly correct but i just  asked on twitter how many shares of gamestop we're
still short apparently they're still 55 billion  shares are so short uh of the 70 million or so
total shares and 47 million in the float um so  something very bad could still happen here i
mean these shorts have not been covered so  this is going to be an ongoing saga where
i think every single platform if if consumers keep  buying these shares what is the end does anybody
have an idea or a prediction on the end game  here and then we'll move on what is the end game
if another five million people buy the shares or  10 million people buy it it goes to a thousand or
two thousand what happens if gamestop is worth  a hundred billion dollars it's such a great
thing that's a great question well can i tell you  jason what that means there's a great article in
the information which sam lesson wrote i don't  know if you guys read it but it basically said
why did tesla win now this is not accurate but i  think his framing is relatively accurate which is
people were buying elon like they  would buy a trading card that's right
and and tesla is a manifestation of elon that's  right um and it actually is so visually it makes
a ton of sense to me like then i think you know  why have like richard branson's businesses worked
or why is the jordan brand work or all the you  know at a smaller level yeah at a smaller level
because we're brands and we have these values  and people can imbue their their collective
decision making and support to the person versus  the institution it's a belief it's a belief in
what that person represents too you know i can uh  why did uh uh mbs buy that freaking painting that
wasn't even a leonardo painting for a billion  dollars you know there was some belief there
you know is it really worth a billion dollars it  doesn't matter at the end of the day most assets
are most assets are purchased under the premise  that i believe the price will be higher tomorrow
than it is today and if we all believe that then  we will all buy it today and we will all find more
people buying it tomorrow that's what bitcoin is  do we all agree though that gamestop is not tesla
i don't agree with your premise i don't think  that stocks necessarily need to be reflective of
the underlying business and that's what so but but  no just think about it that's what's so shocking
about this week because we've all been taught in  these freaking economics books and these financial
analysis books oh the stock is worth x dollars  this kind of cash flow what company has ever paid
out dividends that equal the amount that you paid  to buy the freaking stock unless you lived in 1926
it hasn't happened so everything we've been taught  about dcfs and future cash flows and everything
is nonsense at the end of the day every stock  trades based on the assumption that someone
will pay more for it than i am paying for it  today that is it that is entirely what a stock
is and so if everyone's belief is completely  uncoupled from the underlying asset that that
stock is meant to represent it doesn't freaking  matter and it highlights what's really going on
trading stocks is not investing in businesses and  can i say yeah can i say something else on top of
this jason what was the name of the remember when  we were talking about censorship what was the name
of the the the left podcast that got canceled  on twitter right side uh red scare red scare
is gamestop red scare or at the real donald trump
and my point is who the hell are we to  decide right how does it affect you all
what's your prediction we're sitting  here a year from now full year out
what does gamestop january 2022 look like  what does the stock price look like what is
the business look like what how does this all  resolve itself you know i'm i'm not a public
stock market trader i'm just not i i just feel  like it's i'm not a day trader i don't i don't
buy public stocks it's just kind of like to me  it's a distraction what do you buy this end i
you know just buy vanguard funds like guys if  you're listening to this program and you're
wondering where to put your money just buy  vanguard funds and stop worrying about it
index low fees index yeah low fee index yeah  i mean if you want to bet specific companies
because you get enjoyment out of it do it but  yeah okay so nobody has any idea what happens if
it hits 100 billion or how this ends so i think  that's that's illustrative of my point is that
for somewhat intelligent people who have some  degree of expertise in this area we have no idea
how this ends but this is the box no but this  is the point it is a it is a collective ouija
board moment everyone's got their hand on the  ouija board and they're gonna craft the sentence
any one of us individually cannot predict what  a collective group of three million plus people
are going to do and we've you know we we try and  struggle and think about the underlying value of
a business which is what these hedge funds have  done historically but at the end of the day this
thing is going to be worth what the market tells  you it's worth and what the market chooses to do
we wouldn't know because we are not the collective  three million um jason yeah yeah let me respect so
so look jason there's two questions right there's  always this question of like what should the price
be and then who gets to decide and look do i  personally think gamestop is overvalued yes
of course i think it's going to end very badly but  the question is who gets to decide and is the game
going to be rigged by powerful insiders against  outsiders just it's just like the same question
with parlor okay which is who gets it's not about  which look we can say that there are certain views
that are bad okay but the question is who gets the  power to decide that and it's and and that's what
that's the thing we have to ask is that second  order question of who has the power to decide is
there any outcome amazon got to decide and robin  hood got to decide and the victims were parlor and
gamestop 100 okay so this would be a good segue  to move on uh apparently we had a discussion on
the last episode about running for governor and  uh i bought the domain name governor trimath.com
i had governorjason.com i got governor sachs and  governor freedberg.com and i redirected them and
you guys owned them and they're they're redirected  to your twitter handles and lo and behold we wake
up one day and uh chamath4ca is live chamboth  everybody wants to know jump the gun we were
going to have a vigorous debate and decide which  one to be yeah who's gonna run but somebody jumped
in and i'm not saying other besties might not jump  in other besties could jump in they have domains
stay tuned stay tuned no jason we do not want  to split the bestie vote i think we got all the
best please this is this is the four musketeers  we're all behind now we do not want to split the
bestie vote okay it's on you tell us what's  going to happen now what's going to happen
we are going to do an emergency  pod and talk about exactly that
so if folks want to know they're going  to have to tune in midweek but uh
you put out a platform what's the action  been and no these the reactions been possible
three guys midway i want to be i want to be  very clear midweek midweek but i'll just tell
the quick stories three uh young people um these  three amazing guys just they built it and i just
retweeted it um i can say that tens of thousands  of people have signed up for updates i know that
much um all these three guys though here's the can  i just if i can tell a shout out to these guys um
uh rahul samir and aman all these three guys um  they don't live in california um two did but had
to leave one uh wants to move but can't because  he can't afford it and it's just such a microcosm
of like how beautiful california as a place is  and just what people think about when they think
about the state is just so it's so lovely so for  another time but um anyway shout out to those guys
for building the website thank you so essentially  the entire market has now been driven by a group
of all-in of the all-in army built a website you  retweeted it and that's what this is all about
so there has been no paperwork filed there is  no action committee however it has traction
so it makes one hand and you know i mean  there may be a shadow cabinet meeting maybe
what is the chances well i think chamoth by  publishing that website just went down the
escalator escalator he's gone down the escalator  and who knows what could happen now i'll tell you
this i went on uh i'll i'll do a plug i went on  bloomberg amazing this week amazing hit great
amazing it's on youtube we can put the link to  the show notes yeah put the link in the show notes
nick people need to watch that i went through all  the the the ways in which california is hurting
newsom hasn't done a very good job and i made  my case for chamath so that's a prelude to what
we'll talk about on the next pod but the the  the amazing thing is the outpouring i mean
the number of people who texted me  emailed me and chamath and all of us
like there's a groundswell happening now 100  so you know i would say all the fans of the pod
who are now behind this you guys are making  it real uh free it's pretty crazy manifest
destiny here what's going on is this another  wisdom of the crowds or a mob or a movement
who am i to say are you are you in as chief  science officer will you be our dr fauci you know
here i i think we should have a good debate on  our next pod and hear the platform and discuss the
platform and um you know uh make sure that we all  feel like this is uh uh this is where we should be
um and i think this is gonna take a little bit of  time uh to uh to build um and i think you know the
more we kind of build towards it the more likely  we are to have that ground swell that we're going
to need well let's give the oil in let's give  the old i will tell you it seems pretty likely
that this uh recall effort is going to get the  signatures it needs so we can kind of put that
in the sand that it's very likely we're  going to end up seeing a recall election
okay so if people want to participate in recall  gavin newsom what do they do because that is
the first step yes towards governorship you  gotta go you gotta go to rescuecalifornia.org
rescuecalifornia.org go to that website sign  the petition that is the first step we are very
we only need a few hundred thousand more  signatures we have 1.2 million we need one
point five million go there sign up and then  go to chamas website which is chamath4ca.com
jason i'll make one more point and i think um and  i made this the other day on that clubhouse that
sacks and i did i think we i made it before  you joined if you think about the difference
between a leader and a manager um a manager is  someone who typically delegates uh responsibility
and authority a leader is effective at  synthesizing uh multiple people's points of view
and creates an opportunity defines a vision  defines an objective that is the synthesis
of all the people that that report to him and um  and for which for whom he is responsible or she
and i think what we've seen in california in  particular and really across leadership positions
or governing positions across the country  during this pandemic is a failure of leadership
because when times are predictable if a then  b it is easy to manage and it is easy to look
successful i delegate down to the person who  knows best and they are responsible for the
outcome and they do it well great all i'm doing  is pointing to the right person to run something
the pandemic is difficult and it is unpredictable  it requires a synthesis of economic information
social information and health information and  more often than not a person who typically acts
like a manager points to the person they think  should be in charge under the circumstance to
make a decision and that person is not equipped to  synthesize the economic and social ramifications
of the decision so what we have seen during the  pandemic is most often people in a governing
position have pointed to the health officer or  the medical person and said you make the decision
and that person does not necessarily account  for the social and economic ramifications of the
decision they're making a health person knows how  to save lives the best way to save lives is shut
everything down and so the the test of leadership  during this pandemic has been a test of synthesis
and recommending an action that's associated  with the understanding of the social economic and
health implications of what's going on and that's  really where so many governing um bodies and
individuals have fallen apart during this pandemic  is an inability to do that effectively and i think
that is what is needed going forward it is a  it is a moment of test it is a it is a moment
of truth about the difference between a manager  and a leader and we're seeing across the nation
who is what and i think it is highlighting why  some folks may not be best suited to do this the
second thing i'll say and i know i'm on a little  bit of a diatribe but the second thing i'll say
is career we've been waiting for your diatribe  by the way we took 19 episodes go career career
politicians i think simply should not exist  if you go back to the origins of this country
right having your place in government and we  talked about this over email having your place in
government was meant to be something that everyone  was supposed to take their turn doing and the
people that were sitting in political seats it was  supposed to be the merchant and the local farmer
and the banker and we were all supposed to take  our turn representing our communities representing
our people in government and what we've seen  is people who have made a career out of being
a politician and the result of that is that their  job depends on them getting re-elected in order to
remain in their career they have to get re-elected  and they ultimately end up making trade-offs that
don't necessarily represent the best long-term  interest of their community and this is broadly
true across nations across centuries but it's  particularly acute in the united states where
we've seen such wealth creation over the last  250 years and what's happened is when you have
career politicians sitting in these seats for so  long in an environment of severe wealth creation
you end up having governments that are ineffective  and creating systems that fail us and here we are
and what we need is to have someone go in that's  not dependent on the traditional folks that get
people elected and fund elections and result in  re-elections we need someone that can go in as an
outsider and make a change and so my advocacy  for what's needed in california and i think
nationally and that's a longer conversation is to  find those types of folks to come in and lead and
be politicians that can take a leadership role  synthesize information and not be worried about
the re-election cycle and not have anything to  lose related to a career in politics so i'm done
on that note i want to say i love all of you  and um let's do our emergency pod on tuesday
um do you guys want to play poker tonight i  i'm still in tahoe i was playing that original
graduation you guys come down in town my  mom's in town my parents got vaccinated
yeah i can play i can probably  oh here we go maybe a little
one note if you do fill out if you take if you go  to rescue california.org is that the name yes yes
if you go there you print out the petition and you  hold it up and take a selfie with your signature
on it and you add the besties we will like it  possibly retweet it and possibly follow you
so go ahead and take a picture of your printout  with your name on it and that proves that you're
part of the all-in army and we will like it we  might follow you and we might even retweet you
you could give your besties love you and we'll  see you all next time on the all in pocket
bye-bye see you at couples therapy  tomorrow hey everyone hey everyone welcome
you're talking about real money
these are really big numbers is spread the  opportunity that that technology represents
we're probably gonna have  four kardashians on there you